<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE dif SYSTEM "dif.dtd">
<dif extraction-date="20200929">
<hid>
<!-- **********************************************************************
     
     All material distributed as part of ASHP Injectable Drug Information is copyrighted.
     Reproduction, storage on a retrieval system, or transmission of this material
     or any part thereof in any form or by any means without the express written
     permission of the American Society of Health-System Pharmacists is
     prohibited.
     
     Please contact ASHP Office of Publications at +1 (301) 657-3000
     for more detailed information.
     
     (c) Copyright, 2020, American Society of Health-System 
     Pharmacists, Inc. All Rights Reserved.
     
     ********************************************************************** -->
<hid-mono unit-id="a504013" cpyrt-date="20041001" cx-date="20180629" mono-type="mono">
<unit-num>504013</unit-num>
<intro-info>
<print-class><class-num class-code-ref="48:48" class-text="Vasodilating Agents" /></print-class>
<print-title>Epoprostenol Sodium</print-title>
<full-title>Epoprostenol Sodium</full-title>
<drug-name-info>
<gen-name>Epoprostenol Sodium</gen-name>
<cas-num>35121-78-9</cas-num></drug-name-info></intro-info>
<products><head class="a-head">Products</head>
<para>Epoprostenol sodium is available as a lyophilized powder in vials containing 0.5 mg (500,000 ng) and 1.5 mg (1,500,000 ng) of epoprostenol.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  Several different formulations of epoprostenol sodium products are available; instructions for reconstitution and administration may differ, and epoprostenol stability may vary depending on formulation-specific factors.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup> </para>
<para>Epoprostenol sodium (Flolan, Glaxo; generic, Teva) vials also contain glycine 3.76 mg, sodium chloride 2.93 mg, and mannitol 50 mg.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  Sodium hydroxide may have been added during manufacturing to adjust the pH.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  These epoprostenol sodium vials must be reconstituted and further diluted using only a special diluent that is recommended by the manufacturer.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  Flolan must be reconstituted only with one of 2 special diluents, which are labeled as either &#8220;sterile diluent for Flolan&#8221; (in a 50-mL glass vial) or &#8220;<ital>pH 12</ital> sterile diluent for Flolan&#8221; (in a 50-mL plastic vial).<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  The choice of which of these 2 special diluents is used in the reconstitution and dilution of Flolan affects the drug's stability.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  (See Stability.) Epoprostenol sodium (Teva) must be reconstituted only with the sterile diluent that is labeled as &#8220;sterile diluent for epoprostenol sodium for injection&#8221; (in a 50-mL glass vial).<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  Regardless of the formulation, these vials of special diluent contain glycine 94 mg, sodium chloride 73.3 mg, and sodium hydroxide to adjust the pH in water for injection.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup> </para>
<para>Epoprostenol sodium (Veletri, Actelion) has a differing formulation.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup>  In addition to epoprostenol sodium, vials of Veletri contain sucrose 100 mg, arginine 50 mg, and sodium hydroxide to adjust the pH.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup>  Vials of this formulation may be reconstituted with either sterile water for injection or sodium chloride 0.9% and further diluted with the same diluent used for reconstitution.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> </para>
<para>Each 0.5-mg (500,000-ng) or 1.5-mg (1,500,000-ng) vial of any formulation of epoprostenol sodium should be reconstituted with 5 mL of an appropriate diluent.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  The reconstituted solutions must be diluted prior to administration to provide a final concentration that is compatible with the maximum and minimum flow rates of the infusion pump, the reservoir capacity, and other infusion pump-specific criteria as stated by the manufacturers.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  In general, a 3000- to 10,000-ng/mL concentration of epoprostenol is sufficient to accommodate infusion rates of 2 to 16 ng/kg/min in adults, although higher concentrations may be required for some patients.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup> </para>
<para>The manufacturers&#8217; instructions for preparing various concentrations of epoprostenol from the reconstituted solution using the identical diluent that was used for reconstitution are as follows:<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup> </para>
<para>For 3000 ng/mL, withdraw 3 mL from one 0.5-mg (500,000-ng) vial and add a sufficient amount of diluent to make a total of 100 mL.</para>
<para>For 5000 ng/mL, withdraw the entire contents of one 0.5-mg (500,000-ng) vial and add a sufficient amount of diluent to make a total of 100 mL.</para>
<para>For 10,000 ng/mL, withdraw the entire contents of two 0.5-mg (500,000-ng) vials and add a sufficient amount of diluent to make a total of 100 mL.</para>
<para>For 15,000 ng/mL, withdraw the entire contents of one 1.5-mg (1,500,000-ng) vial and add a sufficient amount of diluent to make a total of 100 mL.</para>
<para>For 30,000 ng/mL, withdraw the entire contents of two 1.5-mg (1,500,000-ng) vials and add a sufficient amount of diluent to make a total of 100 mL.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> </para>
<para>The manufacturers state that higher concentrations of the drug may be prepared for those receiving long-term therapy.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup> </para>
<sect><head class="b-head">pH</head>
<para>Sterile diluent for Flolan has a pH ranging from 10.2 to 10.8; <ital>pH 12</ital> sterile diluent for Flolan has a pH ranging from 11.7 to 12.3.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> </para>
<para> Reconstituted solutions of epoprostenol (Teva) prepared with the provided sterile diluent for epoprostenol sodium for injection have a pH ranging from 11 to 11.8.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup> </para>
<para> Reconstituted solutions of Veletri have a pH ranging from 11 to 13.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> </para></sect>
<sect><head class="b-head">Trade Name(s)</head>
<para><tn>Flolan</tn>, <tn>Veletri</tn></para></sect></products>
<administration><head class="a-head">Administration</head>
<para>Following reconstitution and dilution to the selected final concentration, epoprostenol solution is administered by continuous intravenous infusion through a central venous catheter using an ambulatory infusion pump.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  The drug may be given temporarily by peripheral infusion until a central line can be established.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  The pump reservoirs used should be made of polyvinyl chloride (PVC), polypropylene, or glass.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup> </para>
<para>Epoprostenol solutions prepared with sterile diluent for Flolan or sterile diluent for epoprostenol sodium for injection must be used with a cold pouch if not administered within 8 hours of reconstitution or removal from refrigeration.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  (See Stability.)</para></administration>
<stability><head class="a-head">Stability</head>
<para><bold>Epoprostenol Sodium (Flolan, Glaxo)</bold></para>
<para>Intact vials of the Flolan formulation of epoprostenol sodium should be stored at 15 to 25&#176;C in the carton to protect from light.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  Intact vials of sterile diluent for Flolan and <ital>pH 12</ital> sterile diluent for Flolan also should be stored at 15 to 25&#176;C and should <ital>not</ital> be frozen.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  Flolan must be reconstituted and diluted only with one of these 2 diluents; the reconstituted epoprostenol solutions should not be diluted or administered with other parenteral solutions or medications.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  If not used immediately following preparation, these solutions of epoprostenol should be refrigerated at 2 to 8&#176;C and protected from light.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  The solutions should <ital>not</ital> be frozen; any solution that has been frozen should be discarded.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  Solutions should be visually inspected for particulate matter and discoloration and should not be used if either is noted.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  Vials are for single dose only; any unused solution or diluent should be discarded.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> </para>
<para>Epoprostenol solutions prepared with sterile diluent for Flolan are stable for up to 8 hours when used at 15 to 25&#176;C following reconstitution.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  These solutions may be stored for up to 40 hours at 2 to 8&#176;C prior to use and are stable for up to 8 hours when used at 15 to 25&#176;C following removal from refrigeration; solutions should be discarded after more than 40 hours of refrigerated storage.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  Solutions prepared with sterile diluent for Flolan must be used with a cold pouch if not administered within 8 hours.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  These solutions may be stored for up to 24 hours at 2 to 8&#176;C prior to use and are stable for up to 24 hours when used with a cold pouch that is changed every 12 hours.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  Solutions may be stored at 2 to 8&#176;C prior to use as long as the total combined time of refrigerated storage and infusion does not exceed 48 hours; solutions should be discarded after more than 48 hours of refrigerated storage.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> </para>
<para>Epoprostenol solutions prepared with <ital>pH 12</ital> sterile diluent for Flolan may be administered for up to 72 hours at up to 25&#176;C, 48 hours at up to 30&#176;C, 24 hours at up to 35&#176;C, or 12 hours at up to 40&#176;C, either immediately following preparation or following refrigerated storage at 2 to 8&#176;C for up to 8 days; these solutions do <ital>not</ital> require the use of a cold pouch during administration.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  Solutions prepared with <ital>pH 12</ital> sterile diluent for Flolan should be discarded after 8 days of refrigerated storage.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> </para>
<para><bold> Epoprostenol Sodium (Teva)</bold></para>
<para>Intact vials of this formulation of epoprostenol sodium should be stored at 20 to 25&#176;C in the carton to protect from light.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  Intact vials of sterile diluent for epoprostenol sodium for injection also should be stored at 20 to 25&#176;C and should <ital>not</ital> be frozen.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  This epoprostenol sodium formulation must be reconstituted and diluted only with sterile diluent for epoprostenol sodium for injection; the reconstituted epoprostenol solutions should not be diluted or administered with other parenteral medications or solutions.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  If not used immediately following preparation, these solutions of epoprostenol should be refrigerated at 2 to 8&#176;C and protected from light.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  The solutions should <ital>not</ital> be frozen; any solution that has been frozen should be discarded.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  Solutions should be visually inspected for particulate matter and discoloration and should not be used if either is noted.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  Vials are for single dose only; any unused solution or diluent should be discarded.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup> </para>
<para> Epoprostenol solutions prepared with sterile diluent for epoprostenol sodium for injection are stable for up to 8 hours when used at 15 to 25&#176;C following reconstitution.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  These solutions may be stored for up to 40 hours at 2 to 8&#176;C prior to use and are stable for up to 8 hours when used at 15 to 25&#176;C following removal from refrigeration; solutions should be discarded after more than 40 hours of refrigerated storage.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  Solutions prepared with sterile diluent for epoprostenol sodium for injection must be used with a cold pouch if not administered within 8 hours.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  These solutions may be stored for up to 24 hours at 2 to 8&#176;C prior to use and are stable for up to 24 hours when used with a cold pouch that is changed every 12 hours.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  Solutions may be stored at 2 to 8&#176;C prior to use as long as the total combined time of refrigerated storage and infusion does not exceed 48 hours; solutions should be discarded after more than 48 hours of refrigerated storage.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup> </para>
<para><bold> Epoprostenol Sodium (Veletri, Actelion)</bold></para>
<para>Intact vials of the Veletri formulation of epoprostenol sodium should be stored at 20 to 25&#176;C in the carton and protected from direct sunlight.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup>  The manufacturer states that this formulation of epoprostenol sodium is stable only when reconstituted and diluted as directed with sterile water for injection or sodium chloride 0.9%; the drug should not be mixed with any other drugs or solutions prior to or during administration.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup>  Solutions should be visually inspected for particulate matter and discoloration and should not be used if either is noted.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup>  Vials are for single use only; any unused solution should be discarded.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> </para>
<para>For administration at 25&#176;C, reconstituted and diluted epoprostenol solutions of 3000 to less than 15,000 ng/mL (prepared as directed using 0.5-mg [500,000-ng] vials) may be administered for a maximum duration of 48 hours beginning immediately after reconstitution and dilution or a maximum duration of 24 hours after storage under refrigeration at 2 to 8&#176;C for up to 8 days.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup>  Solutions of 15,000 to less than 60,000 ng/mL (prepared as directed using 1.5-mg [1,500,000-ng] vials) may be administered at 25&#176;C for a maximum duration of 48 hours beginning either immediately after reconstitution and dilution or after storage under refrigeration at 2 to 8&#176;C for up to 8 days.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup>  Solutions of 60,000 ng/mL or more (prepared using 1.5-mg [1,500,000-ng] vials) may be administered at 25&#176;C for a maximum duration of 72 hours beginning immediately after reconstitution and dilution or a maximum duration of 48 hours after storage under refrigeration at 2 to 8&#176;C for up to 8 days.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup>  Short excursions at 40&#176;C are permitted for up to 2, 4, or 8 hours for solutions of less than 15,000 ng/mL, 15,000 to 60,000 ng/mL, or greater than 60,000 ng/mL, respectively.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> </para>
<para>Epoprostenol solutions of 60,000 ng/mL or more (prepared using 1.5-mg [1,500,000-ng] vials) may be administered at temperatures greater than 25&#176;C up to 30&#176;C for a maximum duration of 48 hours, either beginning immediately after reconstitution and dilution or after refrigeration at 2 to 8&#176;C for up to 8 days.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup>  Such solutions also may be administered at temperatures up to 40&#176;C for a maximum duration of 24 hours immediately after reconstitution and dilution.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup>  For solutions with a concentration less than 60,000 ng/mL, the pump reservoir should be changed every 24 hours.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> </para>
<sect><head class="b-head">pH Effects</head>
<para>Epoprostenol is best stabilized in basic solutions,<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2882">2882</a></sup>  and the reconstituted solution becomes increasingly unstable at pH values below the respective normal ranges of each formulation.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  Veletri uses arginine as a buffer, which provides a higher pH than that provided by the glycine buffer in other epoprostenol sodium products (Glaxo, Teva) and likely contributes to the relative improvement in stability.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2882">2882</a></sup>  Flolan prepared with the provided <ital>pH 12</ital> sterile diluent for Flolan results in a reconstituted solution with a higher pH than if prepared with the alternative provided sterile diluent for Flolan and demonstrates increased stability as a result.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> </para></sect>
<sect><head class="b-head">Light Effects</head>
<para>Epoprostenol sodium (Flolan, Glaxo; generic, Teva) as unopened vials and reconstituted solutions should be protected from light during storage.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  The manufacturer of Veletri notes that this formulation of epoprostenol sodium should not be exposed to direct sunlight either in the unopened vial during storage or in solution.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> </para></sect>
<sect><head class="b-head">Filtration</head>
<para>A 60-inch microbore non-diethylhexyl phthalate (non-DEHP) extension set with proximal antisyphon valve, low priming volume (0.9 mL), and inline 0.22-&#956;m filter was used during trials with epoprostenol<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> <sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2881">2881</a></sup>  and is recommended for Flolan administration.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2879">2879</a></sup>  Infusion sets with an inline 0.22-&#956;m filter should be used for the administration of Veletri.<sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2880">2880</a></sup> </para></sect></stability>
<compatibility><head class="a-head">Compatibility Information</head>
<y-site-inj-compat><head class="b-head">Y-Site Injection Compatibility (1:1 Mixture)</head>
<table frame="topbot"><head>Epoprostenol sodium</head>
<tgroup cols="8" colsep="0" rowsep="0" align="left">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="2*" />
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" colwidth="3*" />
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" colwidth="1*" />
<thead>
<row rowsep="1" valign="bottom"><entry colname="col1"><para>Test Drug</para></entry><entry colname="col2"><para>Test Drug Mfr</para></entry><entry colname="col3"><para>Test Drug Conc</para></entry><entry colname="col4"><para>Base Drug Mfr</para></entry><entry colname="col5"><para>Base Drug Conc</para></entry><entry colname="col6"><para>Remarks</para></entry><entry colname="col7"><para>Refs</para></entry><entry colname="col8"><para>Compat</para></entry></row></thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top"><entry colname="col1"><para>Bivalirudin</para></entry><entry colname="col2"><para>TMC</para></entry>
<entry colname="col3"><para>5 mg/mL<a href="#y-si-f1"><sup>a</sup></a> </para></entry><entry colname="col4"><para>GW<a href="#y-si-f2"><sup>b</sup></a> </para></entry>
<entry colname="col5"><para>10 mcg/mL<a href="#y-si-f1"><sup>a</sup></a> </para></entry><entry colname="col6"><para>Physically compatible for 4 hr at 23&#176;C</para></entry><entry colname="col7"><para><sup><a href="a586999.xml#r2373">2373</a></sup> </para></entry>
<entry colname="col8"><para>C</para></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>
<table frame="bottom">
<tgroup cols="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" align="left">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="*" /><tbody>
<row valign="top"><entry colname="col1"><para><a name="y-si-f1"></a><sup>a</sup> Tested in dextrose 5%.</para>
<para><a name="y-si-f2"></a><sup>b</sup> Test performed using the Flolan formulation.</para></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></y-site-inj-compat></compatibility>
<copyright><para>ASHP<sup>&#174;</sup> Injectable Drug Information<sup>TM</sup>. Selected Revisions June 29, 2018. &#169; Copyright, 2020. American Society of Health-System Pharmacists<sup>&#174;</sup>, 4500 East-West Highway, Suite 900, Bethesda, Maryland 20814.</para></copyright>
<refs><head class="a-head">References</head>
<para><xref-external href="a586999.xml">For a list of references cited in the text of this monograph, search the monograph titled <ital>References</ital>.</xref-external></para></refs></hid-mono></hid></dif>
